France,
July 23,
1944,
8.45 a.m.
Lucienne,
my light,
Jeannot,
my love,
it hurts when I think of those wonderful waking moments in Rue de Rennes,
early in our romance.
How happy I was to be your lover,
to see you.
However more wonderful it was,
how splendid and patient you were,
how we craved affection.
Think my life of those days on French soil,
and tell yourself that we shall enjoy a wonderful reunion in France,
and a fresh,
passionate honeymoon.
I'm in your arms,
my young and splendid lover,
mother to my Jeannot,
my comrade,
my essential shining light.
But we shall keep our love fresh and not forget how tough it is to be apart.
I promise you my light,
you who need no promises.
that you will be reunited with the youngest,
most ardent,
craziest lover and beloved.
How badly I want to be near you now.
Kiss our little kid for me.
Sim.
Tour du Monde,
autour d'une table.
Cécilia Reeves,
de la BBC,
William Hague,
de la radio diffusion en Suisse,
Tim Coppens,
de la Voix des Etats-Unis d'Amérique,
Hubert Neumann,
de la KRO Hollande,
Mirek Wierdlicki,
de la radio polonaise,
vous invitent à effectuer en leur compagnie le Tour du Monde,
autour d'une table.
Présentation de Jacques Poliak.
What is this incredible thing I'm hearing?
Cécile,
you have just heard the voice of a future participant in our World Tour show,
the young Richard Simon,
5 years old,
born in Paris,
son of a French mother and a father from America,
our friend Sim Coppens Bravo
I had no choice.
I was on the radio from birth.
Not surprising really.
My dad,
Simon,
was a jazz disc jockey for 50 years.
This is a special program of American music for our French listeners.
Some of you who are listening to us tonight recognized this voice.
20 years ago,
a few thousand French people heard it between the Normandy and Paris coasts.
And this voice is that of Simcoe Ponce,
the most French of the Americans.
If you're a bit like the French Benjamin Franklin,
you won't know if you're Parisian or American.
My role was to walk around the Cote d'Antin with a truck.
A truck that was a kind of radio station,
an ambulance.
I played music,
a lot of music,
especially a lot of great orchestras.
It was in my parents'
house in the Dordogne Valley that I found 63 letters dating from 1944,
written by my father and addressed to Lucienne,
my mother.
My father first came to Lanzac in July 1945.
An American soldier,
he came here with a friend.
Much to the villagers'
surprise,
they improvised a baseball game.
That night,
in a café,
Simon sang the praises of Franco-American friendship.
My parents must have had this memory in mind when they bought this house late in life.
The chances were against Simon and Lucienne meeting,
falling in love,
and living out their days on the banks of the Dordogne.
She,
a French Catholic,
had only gone to secondary school.
He,
an American Jew,
had a PhD.
They couldn't have been further apart,
3,000 miles,
the width of an ocean.
For the
30s, that was huge,
with him in New York and her in Soissons,
north of Paris.
Lucienne is 17 and lives much to her dislike with her father and stepmother in Soissons.
She has been living with them since she was seven,
ever since her parents separated.
Tough times.
Her father has exiled her to the attic to be rid of her and her bad moods until she comes of age.
You're dead to me,
he says.
You no longer exist.
When he says that his daughter is dead,
he knows what he's talking about.
Lucienne's father is a mortician.
Lucienne hates him,
with all her might,
with all her heart,
just as she hates the whole stifling bourgeois world around her.
Her father has always refused to enroll her in high school.
A girl just has to be able to sew.
She isn't of his world.
She's gone into a position in her hideout under the roof.
She won't go to Mass.
She'll never go to Mass again.
A dead girl doesn't go to Mass.
She's got very long braids.
Two braids that won't go to Mass.
In three months,
in exactly 96 days,
she'll cut them off and leave this place.
She'll be 18,
and she won't have to hide her books under her mattress anymore.
I told you that my mother worked here.
Yes.
But before working here,
you need your glasses.
You carefully left them in the office.
It's just a little bit of a mess.
This letter is from 30 July 1932,
sent under the leadership of Nougaret de Lestra in Soissons.
I signed and certified that Miss
Lucienne
Godiard was employed in our house from May 1st 1928 to this day and that she gives us all commitment with a beautiful signature.
And I have a duty to add to this certificate that we are ready to give the best,
I don't know if it's recommendations,
I have trouble,
on Mademoiselle Gaudiard,
excellent employee in every way,
very appreciated by the clients who regret it like us.
I read.
Barely arrived in Paris,
Lucienne finds a job in a bookstore.
Not any old bookstore either.
The Gallimard Bookstore in Boulevard Raspail,
no less.
She loves books,
even closed ones.
She sniffs them,
she strokes them.
It's physical.
The smell of ink and paper.
The perfection of the guillotine.
The sound of pages peeling apart.
The weight of every story and every life.
And the sight of the city through the window.
People enter and leave.
It's alive.
Vous avez le roman d'un tricheur de Sacha Guitry?
Oui,
vous l'avez?
Le vin de solitude d'Irene Némirovski?
And this comedian who follows her everywhere,
he smells the soup,
she doesn't like him.
He's stupid,
he reads Le Figaro.
André Gide passed yesterday,
it's her who served him.
He looked worried.
He spoke quickly and did not pay.
On leaving,
he said,
Thank you,
miss,
for your help.
He gave her a brief,
very brief look,
and stretched his hand towards her face as if to tap her cheek.
Instinctively,
she moved back.
He did not look surprised.
It shocked her that he did not pay.
She would like to tell someone.
Claudia spelling books.
Myrtle lived the young Tarantine.
Her ship carried her to the banks of the Camerine.
There would marriage,
songs and flutes.
have slowly led her to her lover's gates.
The vigilante key had locked away the wedding garland and set her for this day.
Words go round and round in Lucien's mouth.
They are as soft as pebbles.
They'll be nice and ready when the man of her life comes knocking.
Then he'll lie on top of her,
as on a beach in the late afternoon.
He'll feel the warmth she's been storing up all these years.
In the meantime,
she smokes.
Balto cigarettes.
American flavor.
She used to hate the smell of tobacco in Soissons.
Here in Paris,
it's different.
It excites her.
It envelops her.
It puts her mind at rest.
She stubs out her cigarette in a tin can.
She hears the sounds of the city.
The big city she's always dreamed of.
Simon was studying law at Brown University.
He was bored.
One of his professors helped him get a scholarship,
saying,
Go to France and learn French.
He sets off to a foreign land with foreigners.
He speaks Yiddish and English,
no more than three words of French.
Simon may tell himself that his father and mother crossed the Atlantic 30 years earlier in the other direction,
from Lithuania to America,
but he still feels very alone in his gray suit.
Everyone around him is smiling,
so he smiles too.
as though it were nothing to leave behind his family,
his city,
his friends.
Nothing to switch languages.
From his rented room in Rue Soufflot,
Simon photographs the state funeral of Paul Dumers,
the assassinated French president,
passing under his window.
He was revising quietly when the hubbub of the crowd distracted him from his conjugations.
It isn't much fun,
this language,
with as many exceptions as there are rules.
The exam is on Monday.
He's got to finish first or second to keep his scholarship.
He's not remotely competitive by nature.
He wants everyone to win,
everyone to come first.
You could say he's shy,
but that's not quite the right word.
Let's say he's reserved.
Like a table in a restaurant is reserved.
Someone's going to come along.
Someone's going to sit down next to him.
Someone's going to help him.
Reveal him to himself.
When he returns to the United States,
he's in love.
Not with a girl,
but with friends.
Simon's hoarse from shouting outside the campus library all afternoon.
He and two fellow students have organized a rally in support of the Spanish Republic.
He's been handing out flyers and collected $12.
Not bad.
Several students stopped to talk to him.
Only one muttered,
I sure hope Franco wipes you out,
you dirty commie Jew.
He doesn't know what annoys him more,
Franco's brutality or his neighbor's indifference.
He knows he's jeopardizing his PhD.
Horatio Smith,
the head of the French department,
who helps him get a scholarship every year,
doesn't really appreciate this charivari.
That's the word he used,
charivari.
Simon looked up the definition.
A lot of noise.
That suits him.
He's making a lot of noise for the Spanish Republicans.
Not enough,
some would say.
It started raining.
The campus empties.
Tuckville awaits.
Okay,
requesting FBI records.
There we go.
Okay,
so...
Dear...
Freedom of Information Officer.
So,
date range request.
I always thought my father was under surveillance by the FBI.
As I'm no longer a U.S.
citizen,
I asked my cousin Ruthie to help me to officially apply to see his file.
I imagined memos about him being tailed and secret meetings,
a romantic,
shadowy past.
Let me see.
involvement,
affiliations,
memberships.
Possible surveillance during McCarthy period,
1940.
I think that's,
well,
that's basically what I'm looking for.
Okay.
Should we just mail it in?
Mail it.
But the only document I find is a text written for an international conference on the eve of World War II.
In it,
my father,
an American Student Union delegate,
analyzes Jefferson's links to the French Revolution.
No hint of communism,
just an article by a good student.
Going through the papers yesterday,
I think you saw a song that I wrote at that time called
Love in the YCL.
Would you sing it?
Sure.
And that's why members who use to talk about finances.
Now go around discussing their romances.
There's a new intrigue within the league.
It's love in the
YCL.
Fellas and girls are starting to...
discover there's no better place to find your ideal lover.
It's a treat to be kissed by a young communist.
It's love in the
YCL.
Oh, there's a new kid at all our meetings now,
equipped with bow and arrow.
It's little Cupid sending greetings now,
and all our Marxist-Leninists are now becoming feminists.
No time to waste,
just sitting around debating.
Get into the league and start your Christmas mating.
There's a partner cute for each new recruit.
It's love in the
YCL.
This is a picture of active members of the American Student Union.
And one of the activities that we were involved in,
which was raising money to send ambulances to the loyalist side in Spain.
And the campaign on behalf of Spain was a very popular one at that time.
We had many methods of collecting the money.
One of them was to go on the subways.
My brother Mo and
I have memories of the two of us.
going on subways and speaking to the people on the subways and telling them the story of Spain and collecting money,
which we used to send to the loyalist causes.
And we played a role in that campaign.
The Hebrew Rite Rumba rumba rumba The Hebrew Rite Rumba rumba rumba
One night I spent Ay,
call her,
call her One night I spent
I can't I can't I can't I can't I can't I can't I can't I can't
Aikamela,
Aikamela To give culture to the people and the people to culture.
This is the goal of the association to which Lucienne has just joined.
An association made on purpose for paid leave and to knit the alliance,
as it is written in the statutes,
between intellectuals and popular classes.
The popular classes,
Lucienne repeats,
are a whole program.
The bed of the bourgeoisie and the popular layers.
This year,
the corsages are around the neck,
freeing the shoulders.
And Lucienne has beautiful,
very beautiful shoulders.
We urge to ride in the air to say that we believe in it,
that youth brings happiness and that the old world will change.
Lucienne feels at home among these people.
She has finally found a family,
her family,
a sensual and concerned family.
That's them there,
on top of the haystack.
Part of a group,
at last.
She got to the top first and began to sing.
Then everyone climbed up and sang along,
and she thought that love must strike this powerfully,
this high.
that this was what she longed for exactly this this emotion inspired by all the buddies clambering onto the haystacks
20 feet up and singing believing in a better world based on values other than power exploitation and money the man next to her was singing to his name is Pascal and she loves his best voice
She held onto his shoulders for the photo.
She felt a ping in her stomach.
Her foot slipped and he just about caught her.
Another inch and she'd have tumbled to the bottom.
It made her laugh.
She shouts,
Freedom for Spain
He yells,
Freedom for the whole world
She thinks.
Freedom for lips to love and bodies to mingle.
Look at the body.
An extremely elongated body.
Very fusing.
You can understand why someone like Giacometti was shaped.
So we have this ascending effect,
which is very linear,
very romantic.
And yet,
things that are already in the Gothic spirit,
look at the fact that we rediscover the volumes of the human body.
I think of the third woman,
who is,
as we leave the door,
probably the Queen of Saba.
You see,
you have a small belly,
a small overgrowth of the chest.
The neighbors,
the two men who are neighbors,
probably...
David and Solomon,
you see under the dress something on the knee.
We are actually rediscovering the human body and that's a very big moment.
It's true of faces.
So the faces are at the same time very erratic,
as if they had come from the night of time,
fixed.
And at the same time you have the beginning of a smile.
Well,
this same woman smiles.
It may seem nothing,
but it is one of the first smiles that reappears in the history of sculpture for several centuries.
So it's a real blow of tenacity.
The
What's very surprising is that I have four photos of the day the first time my parents met,
which is quite rare.
Yes.
Because of this conference,
this visit organized by a popular front organization called Peuple et Culture.
The two came without knowing each other,
they met there and they did not leave each other until their death.
What surprised me was that there are pictures of this visit,
which become postcards.
It must have been used at the time,
I don't know.
And so my mother wrote the name of the speaker and the date,
which obviously is important,
and the place,
obviously,
important too.
It's him,
just behind Lucienne.
Simon,
it's Simon.
His belly to him and his back to her,
gathered by a thin layer of air.
Him,
perfectly focused on what's going to happen.
Her,
eager to know and to feel.
They don't know yet.
They haven't raised their voice.
They should shake it a little.
She walks on his foot by my guard.
She should introduce herself.
Lucienne turns around.
She doesn't smile like any other comrade would.
The intensity of her look is intimidating.
Simon looks serious.
Almost absent.
Both of them focus on the speaker's words.
We would like to say,
there is before.
There is after,
like a page turning,
a flower blooming.
But no,
it will happen more slowly,
well,
a little more slowly.
He who enters the labyrinth moves seven times back and forth,
in and out,
seven times back and forth,
running his tongue around her mouth seven times before speaking.
Seven times his tongue reaches right to the back of her mouth,
the last step,
otherwise known as the leap of joy.
His tongue on her palate,
such a delicious mouth.
Simon has removed his beret.
He has beautiful,
oyster-colored eyes.
Lucienne greets him like someone tossing a puck to start a game of hopscotch.
The way one rubs the box against the ground so it slides better,
aiming for the square that stands for heaven.
Lucienne makes sure she doesn't tread on the lines.
Simon says a couple of words.
His accent is nice.
He's nice.
Really nice.
Simon goes into his shell the further he moves through the labyrinth.
Are you in Paris for long?
Are you staying for a while?
She loves me.
Lucienne's voice echoes inside him.
She loves me not.
She loves me.
Simon applied for a scholarship to complete his PhD in Paris and his professors approved it.
Where better than the National Library to study French views on American democracy under the Second Empire?
Day after day,
he reads the book.
newspapers from the period and reread Tocqueville over and over again.
But Simon actually has something else in mind.
As soon as he arrives in Paris,
he goes to Trade Union House,
the dispatching office for volunteers who want to fight in the Lincoln Brigade.
The comrades put him off.
Franco's forces may be at the gate of Madrid,
but no more brigadiers are wanted.
When he mentioned the refugees to the pretty brunette he met in Chartres,
she stared at him silently for a while,
then rummaged in her bag and pulled out a card bearing the colours of the Spanish Republic.
Lucien and Simon have come up with a way to meet again soon.
They've undertaken to sponsor two refugee children,
Miguel and Alma,
who are eight and ten.
They're sitting quietly,
waiting for them at the Casa de España.
Two Spanish Basque children,
a French woman,
and an American.
A proper little family.
This colony had been created for orphans,
for abandoned children,
for the lost.
They were almost all Basques.
The Spanish
House, Mrs.
Lola Sacristán,
worked as an administrator.
We called her Mrs.
Lola.
Among other things,
she organized the distribution of clothes when Josephine Baker came.
The famous singer came with a truck full of clothes to give us as a gift,
and Mrs.
Lola distributed them.
In the colony of the House of Spain we had godparents who were French marriages.
My brother and I were always godparents together.
My brother and I had several godparents.
They gave us gifts,
took us for walks,
to the movies,
to eat...
I remember a lady,
who apparently lived alone,
maybe a widow,
who took us out a couple of times.
I also vaguely remember a walk through a fair with another godfather.
The one I remember the most,
because I spent more time with him,
was Le Patron.
They were a couple of low-class social workers,
communists,
sensationalists.
They were very good people,
very...
from the town.
Hello.
You look at yourself,
you look at yourself,
and you look at me again.
I found this old,
all-purpose,
extra-smooth paper notebook.
The page I am sending you,
dated August 3,
1939,
brings back many memories,
good memories.
Last night,
around 8 o'clock,
Simon met Francis and me on Boulevard Raspail,
and we went up to Lucienne Godiard's on the 6th floor.
Lucienne's room is very sweet,
decorated in good taste with an excellent selection of books.
Lucienne,
whom we like very much,
had prepared a most delicious dinner.
Soup,
roast chicken,
cauliflower,
salad,
a good 1927 Bordeaux,
chocolate mousse,
and calvados,
very strong.
After dinner,
we chatted for a long time as a lovely full moon rose slowly over the roofs of Paris.
At last,
we said our goodbyes,
and Francis and I took the U-Bus to the Glacier stop.
It's early summer.
War is on everyone's lips.
But it's early summer.
Simon can think of nothing but Lucienne.
When he reaches the small room,
he's totally paralyzed.
He doesn't move while she undoes his shirt button by button.
He doesn't move while she strokes his chest.
as if he were a girl,
he thinks,
as he runs his hand through her loose hair.
Lucienne's a bit disappointed,
but of course she doesn't show it.
A few days later,
she'll kneel down in front of him,
and again,
he'll wonder what she's doing.
He backs away and makes various excuses to go off and catch his breath.
Lucien says nothing for now.
She doesn't push it.
Slips under the covers.
And turns on her side.
He kisses her back.
He kisses her hands.
He's like a little boy.
He knows nothing of love.
Thank
you.
Honeymoon,
under the bombs.
That might be a nice song title,
but living through it is a different thing.
They're barely reunited,
yet already they must part.
Simon has to return to America because the United States is closing its borders.
Simon translates the circular he's just received.
From September 10th,
only citizens with a passport and married couples may enter the U.S.
I'll never get married.
You hear me,
Simon?
Never.
I'd rather die.
Simon agrees with Lucienne.
He's read Marx and Engels,
and has held forth on the family as a pillar of the class-based society.
Yet he tries to persuade her,
because everyone around him,
his parents,
his brothers and sisters,
is married,
and it hasn't killed any of them.
There are tears and kisses.
Lucienne won't budge a ninch.
For her,
marriage is a synonym for hypocrisy.
If two people truly love each other,
then they don't need to get married.
Monsieur
Pierre Matarasson,
accept to take as your wife
Francine Vormez.
Yes.
Francine Vormez,
accept to take as your wife
Pierre Matarasson.
Yes.
In the name of the law,
I declare you united by the marriage.
Mayor of the 6th arrondissement of Paris,
September 1939.
There is no way to make a dish,
thinks Simon,
who is more and more at ease with the French language.
It is only a formality,
says Lucienne,
a formality to cross the border.
So why does she feel so moved?
Elle est émue parce qu'elle est aimée.
Elle est émue quand Simon dit oui,
même si c'est un oui de papier.
Ils se connaissent depuis quatre mois seulement.
La salle est vide,
immense caisse de résonance.
Lucienne porte son petit tailleur de travail,
celui que Miss Gaines aime bien,
parce qu'il est strict,
dit-elle,
et bien taillé.
Un tailleur bien taillé,
un foulard de couleur.
Simon thinks of his father.
Lucienne is still dazzling.
Not for the families,
they are not there.
Not for the friends,
they are not invited.
She is still dazzling for Simon.
It is simple for him to desire it,
that he cannot resist it.
And on this plane,
on this plane very precisely,
there are progress.
you
They did their level best to travel together,
but it didn't work out.
Not enough money for Lucien's ticket,
so Simon goes ahead.
Simon's eyes are moist.
It might be the evening drizzle,
or he might be missing Lucien.
Everything blurs together.
Burning memories,
searing memories.
The disappointments,
the deep tenderness,
the moments of awkwardness.
When I boarded the boat in Le Havre,
as my father had,
to repeat his October 1939 voyage,
I took with me Stendhal's complete works,
which he had bought to take to New York.
Editions du Divan,
annotated by Henri Martineau in 75 volumes.
A family legend.
These books had crossed the Atlantic twice.
Proof of my father's love of French literature and of his erudition.
Only none of the books had been read.
The pages were uncut.
In 60 years,
neither my father nor anyone else in the family had opened them.
The crossing took six days,
so I had time.
I took a knife and I began.
For five months,
Lucienne has saved up and fought for a ship's berth.
She had to go to Genoa to board the Washington,
the last direct boat to New York.
She knew Paris when she left Soissons.
She had a good job at Gallimard.
Eight years is quite a lot.
She can't really imagine America.
She's leaving everything behind for an unknown world.
For love.
She's leaving everything.
But she finds her father again.
Sometimes you just have to say you're your father's daughter.
She has to admit that right now,
it's good to be the daughter of a French-born Frenchman and a French-born Frenchwoman.
Lucienne gives her identity for the third time with supporting evidence.
A series of uniformed men interview her.
They suspect her of being a Nazi spy.
A spy?
And what if they send her back without even letting her off the boat?
Apparently it's happened before.
One man keeps at her.
He speaks a little French.
Isn't there something fishy about marrying an American citizen on the very cusp of war in Europe?
Simon's waiting on the quayside for her.
She saw him waving his hat and blowing kisses to her a little earlier.
He must be worried.
He isn't allowed aboard,
and she isn't allowed to get off.
It's enough to drive you crazy.
But she must keep herself from blowing her top.
Clench her guts,
keep a grip,
button down.
The situation finally looks like it's been resolved.
Simon is fetched on board to compare their accounts,
one after the other to begin with,
then together.
When he's finally able to take her in his arms,
she bursts into tears.
They have a long,
lingering,
tender kiss.
No one can separate them now.
Now they have to build themselves a nest.
But before that,
they have to get married.
Again.
With a great pomp this time.
It's all arranged.
Lucienne's not angry.
She's just a bit annoyed that she never wanted to get married,
but is now on her second wedding in seven months.
To the same man,
Simon says,
that's not too bad,
is it?
The first wedding was for the papers.
The second is to please the family.
And to please them some more,
she has to pretend she's Jewish.
With this ring,
I join my life with yours.
My commitment to you is strong and without reservation.
I take you to be my lifetime partner,
secure in the knowledge that you will be my constant friend.
Ani Lado-dee.
Ani.
Lado-dee.
Lado-dee-lee.
I am my beloved.
And my beloved is mine.
I taught him everything he knows.
I take it to be my wife.
But not only are two people been married,
but two families have come together.
And I know you've taken them into your hearts as son and daughter and sister and brother.
my friends,
It's also breaking the old life of this couple,
beginning of a new one.
There's also an extra prayer involved here.
That this marriage lasts so the pieces can never come together again.
You better do a good job.
It also puts an exclamation point on the ceremony.
So when you hear the sound of the glass breaking,
join in with a hearty congratulations.
Mazel tov,
or whatever is your expression of joy.
Watch the rapper's hands when I tell you.
Three with your heel.
One,
two,
three.
Uh-oh.
Mazel tov
Is she going to have to remember the names of all these people who come up to her to talk in Yiddish?
For the members of Simon's family talk Yiddish to her,
and the only thing she can do is to lower her gaze,
smile,
and look sweet.
That's what I'm supposed to do,
isn't it?
She asked Simon with a tug on his new tie.
Looks sweet,
like having a wife who looks sweet.
Simon defends himself.
He warned his family that her awkwardness was due to the fact that French Jews were a little bit different from Lithuanian or American Jews.
Lucien interrupts him.
A bit different,
a bit different,
big deal.
Simon leads her over to the stairs.
She should keep her voice down.
She has got to trust him.
Everything will be fine.
She just has to repeat the right lines on the wedding dais,
bending her finger after the ring has been put on,
and drink some wine.
He'll break the glass by stepping on it.
Of course,
Lucien fires back.
If at least I could break it.
I wasn't allowed to be a rabbi when I was growing up.
No women rabbis until the women's movement in 1972.
The first woman rabbi was was...
Are you filming this?
Yeah.
I have to do a better song.
And in 1972,
the first woman rabbi was ordained.
And at that point,
I was an escaping housewife from far,
far away.
And
I came to the city,
and I was,
like,
amazed.
And the women were...
was happening.
And I went to my first women's meeting with six pairs of eyelashes and makeup.
And I said,
I'm going to,
I'm an independent woman.
I came from the suburbs to New York.
And as soon as they started talking,
my mouth dry,
dry open because they were talking about my life.
life.
It was so powerful.
It really informed my life.
The women's movement did that.
And then I became aware of what my connection was for all the other struggles,
all the people that were struggling in the world.
The black struggle was very important.
And I feel very connected to that tradition.
I used to sing with the Black Gospel Choir.
That was one of the first things I did,
was sing with the Black Gospel Choir.
And then the opportunity it came for me to study and I said I want to bring this energy this beautiful and
energy,
this connection that these people have to a spirit.
And I don't care what they call that spirit.
I want to sing.
I want to live with that same kind of passion.
So there's a very strong connection to me between the blues.
I want to sing the blues.
blues to gospel,
you know,
even,
I mean,
it's,
and the,
and the cantorial stuff.
You know,
there's a very powerful,
deep emotion that comes from that.
from both traditions.
So musically,
I'm very connected to both those traditions.
And so the opportunity became,
because the women's movement,
they said,
you can do anything.
Nobody ever said that to me before.
So I decided to study.
The opportunity to become a rabbi came open to me.
And that's what I did and became a rabbi.
I don't even know if my father would like it.
He was so orthodox.
He was so orthodox?
So orthodox.
And he said he wanted to...
somebody say the Kaddish,
you know the Kaddish,
the prayer for the dead.
And I said,
well,
Daddy,
I can say it.
He said,
no,
you have to be,
it needs a man,
you have to be male to sing it.
He had no idea.
And one of the blessings that came to,
you started me talking,
can I continue?
One of the blessings that came to me was that
I did a wedding for this young woman whose father died,
you know,
many years after the wedding,
and she called me up to do the funeral.
But her father wanted his rabbi who was from the Chabad.
It was very orthodox,
separate places for women to sit.
And they were arguing.
I said,
don't argue.
Let him do the ceremony,
and I will talk.
And when I finished talking,
when I came off the dais,
he said to me,
you know,
he said,
we need more rabbis with your neshuma,
with your soul.
And I felt that was my father blessing me.
Because if somebody from the Chabad who was so traditional,
who was so strict,
would say that to me,
then it was a gift to me and for my father.
And I tell this story because it's so meaningful to me.
Hello.
Oh,
I'm going to be a little bit more serious.
Oh
It was simple in the drawing.
Cervix,
finger,
vagina,
all in black and white and clearly marked with arrows.
The doctor had told her and Simon had quickly translated what he said.
The first few times will be a little difficult,
but then a little difficult.
You can say that again.
And then you have to fill the diaphragm with some contraceptive gel,
but how much?
And what's the difference between a teaspoon and a coffee spoon?
Is it bigger or smaller?
Simon is in the bedroom.
He can hear Lucienne swearing at the doctor,
but he doesn't dare go into the bathroom.
Finally,
she calls to him and asks him to bring her a teaspoon.
Can you bring me a teaspoon,
darling?
She likes calling him darling.
It makes her laugh.
He gently opens the bathroom door.
Several times that...
They had my brother and me when they decided to have us.
So they were planned.
We were planned.
A young couple at the beginning of the
1940s.
politically involved,
definitely politically involved,
how would they deal with that?
The birth control movement came out of radical roots.
Margaret Sanger was a radical,
communist,
socialist,
anarchist.
So anyone traveling in those circles would have known where to go.
Not all doctors agreed with birth control,
so you needed to know which one did,
and you needed to know how to ask.
But you could certainly get one,
and you could get contraception legally.
or you could go to a Planned Parenthood clinic.
They could have also used withdrawal or abstinence,
but that's not a desirable way to plan a family for the most part.
Abortion was another form of birth control,
but it was illegal and therefore very dangerous in the United States.
I guess everywhere in that period,
no?
No.
You could get an abortion more easily.
For example,
it was legal in the Soviet Union.
Yes,
so it was the illegal abortion which was so...
Dangerous,
the back alley abortions,
yeah.
I mean the idea,
if you're going to plan a family,
you don't want to plan it after the fact.
You want to prepare ahead of time and during wartime when...
husbands and wives warring together on a regular basis.
The idea was,
do you want to have a family now?
Do you want to wait until the war is over?
Those are considerations.
So birth control becomes an even more important issue.
Oh,
yeah,
I hadn't thought about that.
Sure,
if soldiers coming home on leave spend time with their wives,
but do they want to leave their wives pregnant and alone,
possibly widowed?
The list of all the things they love about each other is far too long.
One about the other,
one with the other.
If they had to make a list to register with a notary,
it would take them ages.
They'd have to note down every detail and record every caress.
But that's not why they're here.
They hold hands,
slightly sullenly.
Jean is sitting on the floor.
What's his father registering with the notary?
How would you explain it to a child?
The child doesn't want to know that his father is off to war and that the business of the men in the dark suit is willed.
But why make a will?
Simon doesn't own anything,
and he leaves everything to Lucienne.
Everything.
Meaning nothing.
This fell next to him.
Wow.
Looks like a piece of shrapnel.
And it fell right next to him,
like 10 centimeters.
So it's like he's not here,
but half a foot away it would have been his plate.
And that's one of the few memories he kept from
Normandy.
Then the other thing are very,
oh,
it's like,
well,
you know,
this is,
this would say,
I guess,
what,
where he is,
where he fought,
or...
There are a couple things on here.
I mean,
I can tell you've got blood type,
but...
Let's see...
His name,
obviously.
Yeah,
his name...
Um,
Simon J.
Coppens?
Right,
okay.
Um,
it looks like,
blood type A?
Is that H?
let me see.
Is it H?
Yes,
yes.
H?
Yes,
that's what I read,
too.
well,
normally they have the religious designation on there as well.
And was your father Jewish?
Yeah.
Okay.
That's what it means.
H is Hebrew.
Okay.
I didn't know that.
Yeah.
That's great.
Well,
thank you.
Sure.
You know,
family memorabilia.
Of course.
Not that much.
No?
No.
Surprisingly,
I mean,
every time,
every once in a while,
somebody will come to the office with the dog tag,
and they want to find out information.
Most of the time,
we can't find anything.
When I was in Belgium,
there was one exception that I found.
A lady,
a Belgian lady brought me in a box,
a wooden box one day,
and it had photographs and letters.
They were all in English,
and it had an address on the outside of the box.
And she told me that there was an American soldier living in her family's house during the war,
and when the soldier left,
he left the box behind.
It was love letters from him to his wife and photographs.
And so...
I mean,
most of the time when people bring stuff like that to us,
we never find out who it belongs to.
But
I saw it had Niagara Falls,
New York on the top of the box.
So I called the clerk of court's office in Niagara Falls.
I talked to the lady.
I said,
you know,
I work at Arden American Cemetery.
I have a name here.
She said,
I'm going to do something I'm not supposed to do.
But she went through her files and she found out some information for me.
And I had to make about 10 phone calls,
but I finally,
I talked to the guy's son,
who was living in Florida,
and his father was still alive.
The next day,
the box was gone.
It was in Florida.
And it arrived on the anniversary of the husband and wife,
and so they got all the pictures and letters and everything back that they had lost for
65 years.
And when those kind of moments,
that still makes me want to cry,
you know?
When I,
to be able to help this veteran with something like that,
it was an amazing moment.
And I just found out he died a couple weeks ago.
His son sent me an email saying thank you for what you did for my father.
Because those kind of things normally don't have happy endings.
When people bring me a dog tag or something like a helmet or something,
most of the time you can't find,
you know,
you can't find any information.
But that was just,
I just got lucky.
June
5th,
1994.
For Richard.
Lucienne wanted our children to be able to say that their father had participated in the war against fascism.
Love,
What
Simon cannot tell,
but will be when they will meet again the object of endless stories.
It is the way he fought in France,
like a soldier,
but without weapons.
He fought with words,
we have already said,
but also with notes,
On June 26,
1944,
Simon descended from a ship.
He got on a small truck equipped with a speaker,
a microphone and a 78-round battery.
In the cities and villages liberated,
where the Germans had confiscated the radio stations,
Simon stopped.
A jazz music came out from the speaker.
People gathered.
A voice gave information.
Information that at first was not good,
and then good,
and then very good.
News from the front,
and then the Marseillaise,
and then the applause.
Is this called propaganda?
Propaganda,
to propagate,
to spread,
to spread.
The light spreads in a straight line,
the sound in every direction.
And
Simon shines the region in every direction.
Next to it is the truck.
The truck that gives information about the liberation of Normandy.
In the cities and villages.
It's a nice document.
Do you recognize the truck?
Yes,
we recognize the truck on its right.
It's a Dodge.
We can see the speaker on the side.
On its left,
there are trucks.
It's a
GMC on its left.
That was his journey.
He was here for two months.
From June 22 to August 20,
approximately.
Based in Colombian.
He marked the names of the cities where he went.
He went there every day,
giving news regularly.
Saint-Laurent,
Colombian,
Rézigny,
Carentan,
Saint-Néry-Eglise,
Montbourg,
Valogne,
Cherbourg,
Bregbec.
Carteret,
Barneville,
Saint Sauveur-le-Viponte,
La Haye-du-Puy,
Lecce,
Perrier,
Coutances,
direction Grandville and Coutainville.
He had traveled the region well.
Yes,
so all this comes from...
It comes from that.
It comes from his road map.
He started...
It's not very regular.
He gives quite a bit of precision on the places,
for example Notre-Dame de...
Seville,
I think.
He says,
we were parked near the post,
in front of the post.
There were about
100 people.
The B&B also,
100-150 people,
so it gives about the population density.
It says here,
very good reception,
enjoy playing the Marseillaise.
Chateau de Colombieres,
July 17th 1944.
My great,
beloved light and my dear sun.
Exactly 13 years ago today,
I boarded the boat in New York to travel to France for the first time.
I had no way of knowing that that voyage would change my whole life and all my plans.
That I'd never become a lawyer and that I'd return to France in 1938 to find my Lucienne.
Neither did I know that I would fall in love with France.
My love is so wonderful,
my life.
I miss you so much.
Kissing,
our great and wonderful passion.
Soon I shall go to bed,
and in my thoughts I shall snuggle into your arms,
to feel the exquisite pleasure of your warm,
loving body.
Quick,
hold me tight,
my Lucienne.
Quick,
all your caresses,
your lips,
your tongue,
above all your beloved hand.
Your beloved hand.
And quick I want to be deeply yours.
For our ecstasy.
To hold your eyes.
And your joy.
I love you so much,
my Lucien.
And I am with you.
Your Sim.
So this is a letter my father wrote to my mother to explain his postal address.
You will read at the top and we will see if it is here.
No
Wait, second mobile radio broadcasting is not true.
Here is the meaning
Headquarters First US Army,
Publicity and Psychological Warfare,
Second Mobile Radio Broadcasting Company.
Ça ne pouvait pas être ailleurs que ici.
J'ai souligné les lettres.
Serre-toi des initiales.
Tout ceci te donnera peut-être une meilleure idée de mes fonctions.
My beloved,
I must leave.
Maybe on the road,
I will have a moment to add something,
maybe not.
Know this,
I take care of myself,
my health is excellent,
my work is a continuous joy.
Despite inevitable troubles that do not come from your people.
The welcome of your people is very affectionate.
Their attitude is splendid.
Really,
the French are happy to see us.
I heard that the national hymns of all the allies are being applauded,
and apparently,
especially,
the Russian ally.
Here,
I have two photos of my father,
one with a friend and one with another.
So this one.
I would like to mention on this photo the sign that your father wears,
which attracts my attention.
It's the famous sign of the OSS,
which is now called the CIA.
So he was well into the psychological war.
Thank you.
Simon is already in Paris,
but Lucienne is still in New York.
She receives a letter every day,
two on a good day.
She sends photos,
which Simon slides into glassine paper pouches inside a small notebook.
Some
nights,
rather than filling the void,
the tenderest words simply enlarge it.
The letters overflow with affection.
Lucienne drowns in her little bed on Long Island.
So she clings to the pictures.
What became of all the people who were on the haystack with her that day?
She thinks of all those who are gone forever.
You'll never see them again.
In France,
Simon seeks to secure Lucien's return to Noéville.
His days are very busy though.
He gives talks about life in America,
celebrates the anniversary of the Commune,
and listens to the Red Army Choir in Cologne.
He collects evidence of their future life as though every step and every movement forged a link between them.
They have to wait another month,
two months,
fourteen months before Lucien is granted permission to return to France.
Jean has turned three by the time she steps off the boat in Le Havre.
Naturally,
everyone weeps,
and we could simply stop the camera there.
On the scared little boy,
they reassure with fairytale words,
they'll never be separated again.
Never.
And for once,
this turns out to be true.
They are never separated again.
They live happily and have many children.
Well,
one more.
The story fades into memories.
No need to invent words to bridge the distance.
No need for tales.
It's enough to say...
I remember.
I remember that Burt Lancaster was an acrobat.
I remember Sem Copin's jazz programs.
I remember that my mother never wanted me to use Simon's letter in a radio program.
She regarded them as too private.
I remember November 1956.
I was nine.
I heard my mother shout,
the fascists are attacking the party.
I remember that my father never wanted to become French.
I remember that at the end of the Algerian War,
my father was afraid of being expelled from France because my brother was a sympathizer of the FLN support networks.
I remember two dinners at home with an attaché from the Soviet embassy in the middle of the Cold War.
And I've always harbored doubts.
Was my father a double agent?
Was the FBI covering for him when they told me his file was empty?
I remember going three times to the Palais des Sports at the Port de Versailles to see the Red Army Choir.
My mother bought me a recording of Kalinka.
I remember that my father got every newly released record,
and I was allowed to sell bad French music to my high school friends on the cheap.
I remember the jam jar in which every day my mother would put the money for the two packets of Pall Mall my parents no longer smoked.
those savings paid for the first
furniture in our house in Lanzac.
I remember that my mother watched over my father's diet three times a day for 27 years to control his diabetes.
He was allowed one piece of chocolate a week and an apple a day.
I remember their enthusiasm when they returned from their first trip beyond the Iron Curtain to Budapest in 1986.
Every market had apples.
I remember one spring afternoon in 1972,
my father frantically buttoning up his pajamas and shutting their bedroom doors.
I don't remember if Simon and Lucienne wore wedding rings.
I have to call my brother and ask him.
I remember that the Suyak Jazz Festival decided to rename itself the Simcoe Pants Jazz Festival in 1985.
Here we say they were fighting each other,
they admired each other a little,
they were fighting each other,
that was a bit it.
They were surprised in attitudes that were love attitudes.
Well,
they had discretion that is good,
but it had struck us at the time.
Maybe not mentioned,
but really,
we felt them close,
they held each other by the hand.
When they were going to walk,
it was touching.
It could be an example.
Yes,
because we are not the same.
For many years there was corn in the field between the house and the river where my father played baseball in 1945.
Then they planted walnut trees.
But it's rained a lot this summer.
The neighbors complain the harvest will be later than usual.